<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/feed_style.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="https://www.rssboard.org/media-rss">
  <channel>
    <title>Cars on Abdullah Salameh&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/cars/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cars on Abdullah Salameh&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/cars/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><icon>/logo.svg</icon>
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Charging the BYD Seagull: How 8A and 32A Chargers Impact Its LFP Battery</title>
      <link>/posts/charging-the-byd-seagull-how-8a-and-32a-chargers-impact-its-lfp-battery/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/charging-the-byd-seagull-how-8a-and-32a-chargers-impact-its-lfp-battery/</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>The BYD Seagull is a compact electric vehicle equipped with lithium iron phosphate (LFP) batteries, known for their durability and thermal stability. Understanding how different charging rates affect these batteries is crucial for optimizing both vehicle performance and battery longevity.</p>
<h2 id="byd-seagulls-charging-capabilities">BYD Seagull&rsquo;s Charging Capabilities</h2>
<p>The Seagull offers two battery options: a 30.08 kWh LFP battery and a 38.88 kWh LFP BYD Blade battery. Its charging infrastructure supports:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>AC Charging</strong>: Up to 6.6 kW</li>
<li><strong>DC Fast Charging</strong>: 30 kW or 40 kW</li>
</ul>
<p>These specifications indicate that the Seagull is designed to handle various charging scenarios, from standard home charging to faster public charging stations.</p>
<h2 id="understanding-c-rates-and-their-impact">Understanding C-Rates and Their Impact</h2>
<p>The C-rate measures the rate at which a battery is charged or discharged relative to its capacity. A 1C rate means charging the entire battery in one hour. For the Seagull&rsquo;s 30.08 kWh battery:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>1C Rate</strong>: 30.08 kW</li>
<li><strong>0.5C Rate</strong>: 15.04 kW</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="charging-with-an-8a-charger">Charging with an 8A Charger</h2>
<p>An 8-ampere (A) charger operating at 230 volts (V) delivers approximately 1.84 kW (8A × 230V). This translates to a C-rate of about 0.061 for the 30.08 kWh battery (1.84 kW ÷ 30.08 kWh). Such a low C-rate is considered gentle on the battery, minimizing stress and potentially extending its lifespan.</p>
<h2 id="charging-with-a-32a-charger">Charging with a 32A Charger</h2>
<p>A 32A charger at 230V provides around 7.36 kW (32A × 230V). For the 30.08 kWh battery, this results in a C-rate of approximately 0.245 (7.36 kW ÷ 30.08 kWh). This rate is still within the battery&rsquo;s designed AC charging capacity of 6.6 kW, meaning the vehicle’s onboard charger will regulate the charging power accordingly.</p>
<h2 id="research-insights-on-lfp-batteries-and-charging-rates">Research Insights on LFP Batteries and Charging Rates</h2>
<p>Studies have shown that LFP batteries exhibit resilience to higher charging rates. For instance, research indicates that charging at rates up to 4C does not significantly impact the battery&rsquo;s lifespan. Specifically, capacity degradation was 15% at a 1C rate and 17% at a 4C rate after 4,000 cycles, with similar degradation observed up to 1,000 cycles.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>The BYD Seagull&rsquo;s onboard charger supports a maximum AC charging power of 6.6 kW. This means that when using a 32A charger at 230V (which can provide up to approximately 7.36 kW), the vehicle&rsquo;s charging system will limit the power to 6.6 kW to stay within its designed capacity. Charging at this rate aligns with the vehicle&rsquo;s specifications and should not adversely affect the longevity of its lithium iron phosphate (LFP) battery. Therefore, utilizing a 32A charger is considered safe and appropriate for maintaining the battery&rsquo;s health.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BYD_Seagull">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BYD_Seagull</a></li>
<li><a href="https://findingspress.org/api/v1/articles/21459-impact-of-charging-rates-on-electric-vehicle-battery-life.pdf">https://findingspress.org/api/v1/articles/21459-impact-of-charging-rates-on-electric-vehicle-battery-life.pdf</a></li>
<li><a href="https://moscow.sci-hub.ru/5155/011d5b81780c4ac3e787a937c78bd05a/10.1016@j.jpowsour.2016.04.140.pdf">https://moscow.sci-hub.ru/5155/011d5b81780c4ac3e787a937c78bd05a/10.1016@j.jpowsour.2016.04.140.pdf</a></li>
<li><a href="https://acmobility.ph/news/byd-seagull-launch">https://acmobility.ph/news/byd-seagull-launch</a></li>
</ul>
]]></description>
      
    </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>
