<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/feed_style.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="https://www.rssboard.org/media-rss">
  <channel>
    <title>Electronics on Abdullah Salameh&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/electronics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Electronics on Abdullah Salameh&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/electronics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><icon>/logo.svg</icon>
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Capacitor Charging and the Concept of Full Charge</title>
      <link>/posts/understanding-capacitor-charging-and-the-concept-of-full-charge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/understanding-capacitor-charging-and-the-concept-of-full-charge/</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>While taking a <a href="https://youtube.com/playlist?list=PLww54WQ2wa5qVh1p8iPi7HspX7N9hbvbc&amp;si=9h1KH2NZG2lSLsaB">course with Waleed Essa</a>, we explored the fascinating behavior of capacitors. During one of the experiments, an interesting observation about capacitor charging sparked my curiosity. My friend <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ahmad-awad-36b481301/">Ahmad Awad</a> and I decided to dive deeper into the topic, conducting research that ultimately led to this blog.</p>
<p>When analyzing capacitors, we often hear that a capacitor is &ldquo;fully charged&rdquo; when the elapsed time equals 5 times the time constant (“5τ”). However, upon closer look, this statement needs some clarification. Let&rsquo;s dive into the theory, practical observations, and what &ldquo;fully charged&rdquo; really means.</p>
<h2 id="observations-from-the-simulation">Observations from the Simulation</h2>
<p><img src="/images/Pasted%20image%2020250121022953.png" alt="Image Description">
<img src="/images/Pasted%20image%2020250121023020.png" alt="Image Description"></p>
<p>In a recent calculation, the capacitor was expected to be fully charged in 0.25 seconds. However, the voltage across the capacitor at this point was 11.923 V instead of the expected 12 V. The error was calculated as:</p>
<p>${(12-11.923)/12}*100 = 0.6$%</p>
<p>This raised the question: Why is there an error when the capacitor is supposed to be fully charged at 5τ?</p>
<h2 id="the-truth-about-5τ">The Truth About 5τ</h2>
<p>The value of 5τ does not mean the capacitor is 100% charged. Instead, it means the capacitor has reached about 99.3% of its maximum voltage. Using the data from the simulation, we can confirm this:</p>
<p>$11.923/12 * 100 = 99.33$%</p>
<p>This matches the theoretical prediction. While the capacitor seems nearly charged at 5τ, it never fully reaches 100% because of the exponential nature of its charging curve.</p>
<h2 id="theoretical-explanation">Theoretical Explanation</h2>
<p><img src="/images/Pasted%20image%2020250121015614.png" alt="Image Description"></p>
<p>The voltage across a charging capacitor is given by the equation:</p>
<p>$V(t) = V_{max}(1-e^{-t/RC})$</p>
<p>where:</p>
<ul>
<li>$V_{max}$ is the maximum voltage the capacitor can charge to (12 V in this case).</li>
<li>$t$ is the time elapsed.</li>
<li>$RC$ is the time constant of the circuit.</li>
</ul>
<p>As time passes, $e^{-t/RC}$ gets closer to zero.
<img src="/images/Pasted%20image%2020250121015737.png" alt="Image Description">
This means it would take infinite time for the capacitor to reach exactly $V_{\text{max}}$. In practice, we consider the capacitor &ldquo;fully charged&rdquo; when it’s close enough to $V_{\text{max}}$, such as 99.3% at 5τ.</p>
<h2 id="the-simulation-discrepancy">The Simulation Discrepancy</h2>
<p><img src="/images/Pasted%20image%2020250121020039.png" alt="Image Description"></p>
<p>Interestingly, the simulation showed the capacitor reaching exactly 12 V, which seems to go against the theory. Why did this happen?</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Oscilloscope Precision:</strong> Oscilloscopes show voltages with limited precision. If the capacitor voltage is extremely close to the maximum (e.g., 11.999999 V), the oscilloscope rounds it to 12 V.</li>
<li><strong>Rounding Effects:</strong> The actual voltage might still be slightly below 12 V, but the measuring device’s resolution hides these small differences. Higher-resolution equipment would show the tiny gap.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="key-takeaways">Key Takeaways</h2>
<ul>
<li>At 5τ, a capacitor is 99.3% charged, not 100%.</li>
<li>It would take infinite time for a capacitor to reach exactly $V_{\text{max}}$.</li>
<li>Simulations and measurements often show $V_{\text{max}}$ due to rounding and device limitations.</li>
<li>This approximation is fine for real-world use, as the difference is too small to matter.</li>
</ul>
<p>Understanding these details gives a clearer picture of how capacitors behave and avoids common misunderstandings about what &ldquo;fully charged&rdquo; means.</p>
]]></description>
      
    </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>
