<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/feed_style.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="https://www.rssboard.org/media-rss">
  <channel>
    <title>Tag2 on Abdullah Salameh&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/tags/tag2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tag2 on Abdullah Salameh&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="//localhost:1313/tags/tag2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><icon>//localhost:1313/logo.svg</icon>
    
    
    <item>
      <title>About me</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//localhost:1313/about/</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>Hello, and welcome to my blog! I&rsquo;m an aspiring <strong>Electrical Engineer</strong> with a passion for combining creativity, innovation, and technology to solve real-world problems. I recently completed an internship as a <strong>Full Stack Developer</strong> at <strong>Inspire for Development Solutions</strong>, where I honed my skills in modern web development. Currently, I’m an intern at <strong>HTU Hacker Space</strong>, focusing on cutting-edge electrical engineering challenges.</p>
<h2 id="a-little-about-my-journey">A Little About My Journey</h2>
<p>With a foundation in <strong>Electrical Engineering</strong>, I’ve explored various disciplines, including <strong>full-stack development</strong>, <strong>robotics</strong>, and <strong>app development</strong>. During my time at Inspire, I worked extensively with <strong>React</strong>, <strong>Redux</strong>, <strong>Node.js</strong>, and <strong>MongoDB</strong>, developing impactful solutions. Now, I’m diving deeper into the world of electronics and embedded systems at HTU Hacker Space.</p>
<p>Some highlights from my journey include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Developing a <strong>Job Portal Web Application</strong> with features like CV building, job posting, and application tracking.</li>
<li>Designing and building an <strong>Arduino-based environmental monitoring system</strong> with temperature, humidity, and soil sensors.</li>
<li><strong>CaReminder - Smart Pill Dispenser:</strong> A smart device integrated with a mobile app to streamline medication management, featuring precision dispensing, real-time notifications, and SolidWorks-designed components.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="my-tech-toolbox">My Tech Toolbox</h2>
<p>Here’s a glimpse of the tools and technologies I work with:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Frontend:</strong> React, Redux, Material-UI (MUI), Expo</li>
<li><strong>Backend:</strong> Node.js, Express, MongoDB</li>
<li><strong>Hardware:</strong> Arduino, ESP32, DHT11 sensors, LCD modules, custom control circuits</li>
<li><strong>Design and Simulation:</strong> SolidWorks, PCB Design</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="beyond-work">Beyond Work</h2>
<p>Outside of engineering, I love drawing, watching movies and TV shows—two of my favorite series are <em>Breaking Bad</em> and <em>Arcane</em>. In my downtime, I enjoy playing video games, with <em>Cyberpunk 2077</em> and <em>Red Dead Redemption 2</em> being among the best games I’ve ever played. I’m always excited to learn, collaborate, and build innovative solutions that make a difference.</p>
<p>Feel free to explore my blog to see more about my projects, thoughts, and journey!</p>
]]></description>
      
    </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>
